[Music]
learning to play the piano so that you
are actually good at playing the piano
takes quite a long time and if you're
anything like I was you don't want to
waste any time and you want to get as
good as possible as quick as possible so
in today's video I'm going to tell you
exactly what I would do if I was to
start learning the piano all over again
and at the end of the video I'm also
going to walk you through how I would
organize a practice session to learn as
quickly as possible so let's get into it
so if I was starting again the first
thing I would do is sight read something
every day when I first started learning
the piano I did zero site reading
whatsoever and as a result of that I was
actually really pretty terrible at
reading music and the reason for that is
because most of the time that I spent
learning I spent learning by ear and I
was actually very good at making stuff
up on the piano and also playing songs
by ear but my ability to read music
quickly was actually really quite bad
and that was all the way through from
when I started learning the piano until
I was 18 years old when a teacher said
to me that he didn't care about my
ability to site read he only cared about
my ability to learn pieces of Music
quickly and that was kind of interesting
to me cuz I'd never really put two and
two together and worked out that the
whole point of site reading is to be
able to read stuff quickly which sounds
stupid but then again I am stupid so
then I decided that I was actually going
to spend some time really focusing on
getting better at site reading music and
so I got a load of secondhand music and
it was a stack about this size and every
day I would read through one new piece
of music that I've never seen before and
only play it once because the whole
point of site reading is that you're
trying to instantly recognize notes
instantly recognize patterns and be able
to read it instantly and the whole
purpose of me doing this was not
actually to get good at site reading it
was me trying to get good at recognizing
things on the page quickly so that I
could learn pieces of music quicker so
if I was to start learning the piano
again then I would sight read something
every day because although site reading
is pretty painful and in the moment it
feels like you're just failing all the
time if I had got into the habit of site
reading music every day then I would
have been very good at reading music
much earlier and I would have worked my
way through a lot more pieces and got
better at the piano much faster another
thing that I would do is focus on
playing correctly now once again this
sounds kind of stupid and once again
that is because I am stupid so I often
need the obvious pointing out but when I
first started playing the piano I didn't
really care about how I was playing the
notes or what I was actually playing I
just wanted to be able to play the piece
of music as fast as I could but as I got
better at the piano I realized that a
problem that I solve now is a problem
that I don't don't need to solve later
so if I play through a piece of music
now and I find something that's
challenging or I find something that I'm
getting wrong then I immediately focus
on that specific thing because if I fix
that now then if it comes up again in
another piece or later in that piece of
music then I've already solved the
problem whereas when I first started
learning I would play through a piece of
music from start to finish make lots of
mistakes and then if I came across those
problems in another piece they would
still be there and I'd still be making
those mistakes and if you play the same
mistake lots of times times then you're
just reinforcing that mistake rather
than reinforcing the correct thing
another thing that I would do if I was
starting again is I would categorize the
problems that I have into three
categories the first category is
technical problems the second category
is musical problems and the third
category is knowledge problems now
knowledge problems are pretty easy to
fix because all you have to do is learn
the thing so for example if you see an
Italian word in a piece of music then
learn what that Italian word means
although you'd be surprised how many
people don't know the words that are in
the piece of music that they're learning
because they've never thought to look it
up fixing musical problems is things
like fixing Dynamics so how loud you're
playing or fixing articulation so is
something really short and spiky in
staccato or are you supposed to connect
all the notes those kind of musical
problems that characterize a piece of
music I would fix by isolating the
section that has that musical problem
for example if there is four bars where
I'm forgetting to play quietly and I'm
supposed to be playing quietly I would
only play those four bars over and over
again quietly so I'm reinforcing the
dynamic that I'm supposed to be playing
and when playing through that piece it
happens automatically and the same if
there is a Stato section in a piece of
music where all of the notes are short
and spiky I would isolate that section
and make sure that they're really
staccato so once again when it comes to
playing that piece through you do it
automatically and then there are
technical problems which are problems
where your hands just won't do what you
want them to do technical problems tend
to take more than one practice session
to fix because you're trying to get your
hand to do some something new that it's
not used to and if you categorize your
problems and know that the problem that
you're having is a technical problem
then it becomes much easier to
rationalize and fix and there's a couple
of ways that I would fix technical
problems depending on what that problem
is for example if you have a series of
really fast notes that your hands are
struggling to play you can play a long
series of fast notes slowly so that your
hand gets used to where it's got to go
or you can play really small sections of
those fast notes quickly so that you get
used to playing it at the speed it's
supposed to be at or you might have
something like a really jump in a piece
of music and to fix that I would isolate
the problem and just do the jump and
then when you are comfortable with that
you can run into the jump and stop one
no after the jump but one of the best
ways to fix technical problems is to
create your own exercises out of that
problem for example if you find a
difficult jump in a piece like that then
you could turn that into an exercise by
playing it through
scales this will mean that you not only
fix the problem in that context but you
you also get better at that skill in
general so if you come across jumps in
another piece your hands will be much
more equipped to deal with it another
thing that I would do if I was starting
over again is to set clearly defined
short-term goals most people know when
they start learning the piano that they
want to learn the piano thanks Captain
Obvious but unless you are doing grades
you don't often have something that's in
the near future to aim towards when I
was learning the piano the first grade
that I actually did was grade eight and
this meant from starting the piano all
the way up to being pretty good at the
piano I didn't have anything really to
aim towards and that can work for people
who have the mental strength of a lion
like I do but for most people learning
the piano can become very daunting very
quickly when you realize you've got a
long way to go if you've got nothing in
the short term to aim towards so if you
are someone who is playing without doing
grades or anything like that then a good
idea is to try and perform to at least
one person maybe three or four times a
year and prepare a handful of pieces to
perform another good way of having
things to prepare for is maybe starting
a YouTube Channel and playing a series
of pieces for a video or posting your
performances in a learner piano group a
short-term goal can be whatever you want
it to be but for me I definitely would
have benefited from having deadlines
where on a date I have to have learned
pieces of music by another thing that I
would have learned to do if I was
starting all over again is to learn how
to identify chords in a piece of music
now because I started learning the piano
by playing by ear and understanding
chords was something that I was pretty
good at it never crossed my mind when
learning a piece of music by reading it
that that piece of music was also made
up of chords and Melodies which sounds
pretty stupid but that's because I am
pretty stupid the interesting thing
about chords in a piece of music is that
most of what you are looking at are
notes that form chords even if you
aren't playing chords directly together
like this where you have three notes at
the same time you might see a piece of
music that is something like
this and all of those notes together
form a chord being being able to
understand chords in a piece of written
music not only helps you understand what
you are playing in terms of how it feels
is it a major chord is it a minor chord
what does that tell you about the piece
of music but it also actually makes
reading the piece of music a lot easier
site reading and reading pieces of music
is not just about reading individual
notes if you can see larger patterns and
most of those patterns are chords then
you can start to read groups of notes
rather than individual notes and also
you can predict what's going to happen
next in the music because there are
certain chord patterns that happen in
all types of music and another thing
that I would do if I was starting over
again and this is something that I
actually did do but I would include
anyway because it was the most
beneficial thing for me and that is to
make time for messing around on the
piano this kind of depends on what type
of player you are there are people who
only mess around on the piano and there
are people who never mess around on the
piano and what I mean by messing around
is just playing for fun and playing
without music playing without any real
intention but just to find chords that
you like the sound of and improvise with
them or work a song out by ear and mess
about on the piano with the chords that
you've worked out if you want to really
be able to understand music there is no
real better way than just messing around
with the instrument it's a bit like if
you were trying to learn a different
language you can learn the individual
words and you can piece sentences
together but the only way that you
really get to know that language so that
you are fluent in the language is by
having an improvised conver ation with
someone else so if I was starting again
while most of my practice would be your
standard reading learning pieces that
kind of thing I would always make time
for just messing around on the
instrument because that is fun it's
going to help you be able to play with
other people and it's going to teach you
more about chords and scales than
anything else so how would I actually
organize a practice session if I was
going to start from scratch today well I
would divide practice into three
sections I would have scales and
Technical exercises I would have site
reading and then I would have pieces and
I would mess around on the piano in
between practice sessions scales and
Technical exercises are the best way of
helping you improve your Technique
generally and your understanding of how
scales work that would seem to be
self-evident so when you are playing a
piece of music that uses a certain scale
then your hands are very accustomed to
which notes you're going to be using on
the piano and they're also a really good
way of warming up because they really
get your fingers to move before you have
to play something that's a bit more
mentally demanding I would also include
here any technical exercises that you've
made up from problems that appear in
your pieces because building technique
in your fingers takes a bit of time
practicing these as kind of a warm-up
means that you're isolating it from the
piece of music that you're learning and
it means over several days you can get
good at that technique without getting
frustrated that it's not working when
you play it in the piece then I would
spend 20% of my time doing site reading
and I would just try and find some
random super easy music and play through
it if you are an absolute beginner I
would recommend my site reading book
which there is a link to in the
description has 4 20 exercises where you
can just play through them one by one or
you can just find any super easy music
and just play through it only once in
site reading mistakes aren't really the
issue as long as you keep going the more
site reading you do the more you'll
notice a similar mistake come up for
example if you are struggling to read
jumps between two distant notes
eventually with enough site reading
practice it will click but going back
and fixing problems means that you're
not really sight reading anymore so I
would find some super easy music play
through it once and then I would move on
to pieces and the reason that I would
spend most time learning pieces is
because not only is that the place to
practice musicality but you are also
applying your ability to site read and
your ability to play scales all in one
thing and learning pieces can be divided
into two different sections firstly
learning new notes and secondly fixing
old notes I would personally start by
learning new notes because if you start
playing through the piece of music that
you can already play you can get stuck
in only fixing problems in a section
that you already know and it's
worthwhile dedicating a bit of time to
learning a new part of the piece and
then when it comes to fixing old notes
notes that you can already play in that
piece of music I would play through that
section once and try and make notes of
any problems and work out whether that
is a knowledge problem a musicality
problem or a technique problem if it's a
knowledge problem then lock it up if
it's a musicality problem then isolate
the section and practice that specific
musicality problem and if it's a
technical problem then turn it into an
exercise or isolate the problem so that
you are playing a small amount of notes
quickly or a larger amount of notes
slowly depending on what the problem is
so that is what I would do if I started
learning the piano all over again if you
want to see how well my subscribers play
the piano then head on through and I
will see
you there